Guide to the Rice University Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Department records, 1963-2008 UA 328
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Department records
1963-2008
1980-2008
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Department
UA 328
5 Linear Feet (3 boxes, 1 oversized box)
Ecology and Environmental Biology records, including, but not limited to, Annual Reports, Budget Reports, Space Surveys, Faculty and Graduate Recruitment files, Correspondence and Memos. Also includes files and Annual Reports from the last decade of the Biology Department. Faculty members represented include, but are not limited to, Kathleen Matthews, Paul A. Harcombe, Ronald Sass, Stephen Subtelny, and Charles Philpott.
Biographical / Historical
The Biology Department at Rice University formed in 1912 with Julian Huxley named the first Professor of Biology. His name is commemorated by the department's Huxley Fellows Program, a fellowship for recent Ph.D. recipients. In 1989 the Biology Department became The Ecology and Evolutionary Biology (EEB) Department; this transition is well documented in the Annual Reports leading up to and immediately following the formation of the EEB Department, from 1985 to 1992. Today the department focuses on plant/insect interactions, molecular evolution, genomics, and the biology of plants, insects, and microbes. Recent research has examined environmental issues, such as ecosystem degradation and global warming, and their actual and potential effects on the environment. The department offers M.S., M.A., and Ph.D. Degrees to graduate students and B.A. and B.S. degrees to undergraduates. The graduate programs seek to build strong relationships between faculty and students, while the undergraduate degrees look to inspire a sense of environmentalism within its students. The EEB Department is housed in the Anderson Biology Lab with a recently renovated greenhouse next to the lab building.
Scope and Contents
Ecology and Environmental Biology Department and Biology Department files documenting daily routines of the department, specific faculty members' memos, and graduate student recruitment and admissions. Includes Annual Reports from 1983 to 1999 and 2002 to 2003 and Budget Reports 1989 to 1996 and 1999 to 2000. Changes in the department are well documented, showing the transition from Biology to Ecology and Environmental Biology, renovations of M.D. Anderson Labratory, Space Surveys, Office Relocations, and memos on the Biological Prairie and Aviary at Rice University.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to Woodson Research Center, 2013.
Index Terms
Subjects
Biology; Ecology; Universities and colleges
Document Types
reports; letters (correspondence); memorandums
- Series I. Alphabetical Files, 1963-2008, 165843
  - Annual Report, 1983; 165844 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report, 1984; 165845 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1985; 165846 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1986; 165847 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report, 1987; 165848 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report, 1988; 165849 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report, 1989; 165850 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report, 1990; 165851 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report, 1991; 165852 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report, 1992; 165853 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report, 1993; 165854 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report, 1994; 165855 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report, 1995; 165856 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Report, 1996; 165857 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Report (1 of 2), 1997; 165858 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual Report (2 of 2), 1997; 165859 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Annual Report, 1998; 165860 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Annual Report (1 of 2), 1999; 165861 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual Report (2 of 2), 1999; 165862 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annual Report (1 of 2), 2002; 165863 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Annual Report (2 of 2), 2002; 165864 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Annual Report, 2003; 165865 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Available Funds, 2004; 165866 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Aviary and Bird Research, 1993; 165867 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Biological Prairie, 1991; 165868 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Biology Lecturer Positions, 1980-1988; 165869 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Biosciences Computer Lab, 1993; 165870 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Brochures, 1989; 165871 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Budget Reports, 1989-1990; 165872 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Budget Reports, 1990-1991; 165873 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Budget Reports, 1991-1992; 165874 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Budget Reports, 1993-1994; 165875 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Budget Reports, 1994-1995; 165876 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Budget Reports, 1995-1996; 165877 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Budget Reports, 1990-2000; 165878 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Building Layouts and Floorplans, 1990-1995; 165879 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Campus Microcomputer Software Licenses, 1992; 165880 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Campus Network, 1993; 165881 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Capital Budget Request Forms, 1998-2004; 165882 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - CGS/GRE Survey, 2004; 165883 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Commencement Information, 1999; 165884 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Computing Request Forms, 1993-1994; 165885 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Conservation Biology, 1993; 165886 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1992; 165887 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1998-1999; 165888 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 2004; 165889 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, P.A. Harcombe, 1991; 165890 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Course Budgets, 1989-1995; 165891 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Course Schedule, 1995-1996; 165892 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Course Schedule, 1998-1999; 165893 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Counseling Services for Graduate Students, 1992; 165894 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Department Factsheets, 1993-1994; 165895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Department Hardware, 1992; 165896 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Department Office Furniture Installation, 2004; 165897 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Department Software, 1990; 165898 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Educational Computing, 1990-1994; 165899 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Facility Maintenance, 1991-1992; 165900 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Minutes, 1998-1999; 165901 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Recruitment, 2002-2003; 165902 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Positions Advertisements, 2003-2004; 165903 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - FEP Survey, Hazardous Materials, 2006; 165904 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Final Exam Information, 1998-1999; 165905 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Final Exam Information, 2000; 165906 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Five Year Plan, 1993; 165907 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fundraising, 1991-1992; 165908 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fundraising, 1992-1993; 165909 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gifts, 1992; 165910 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Graduate Admissions, 1998-1999; 165911 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Graduate Degree Information, 1999; 165912 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Graduate Future Plans (1 of 2), 1999; 165913 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Graduate Future Plans (2 of 2), 1999; 165914 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Graduate Recruiting, 1988-1992; 165915 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Graduate Recruiting, 1994-1995; 165916 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Graduate Tuition and Stipend Information, 1989-1992; 165917 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Infrastructure Renovation, NSF Grant, 1992; 165918 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Inventory, 1990-1991; 165919 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Inventory, 2007; 165922 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Inventory, 2008; 165923 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Inventory, Computers, n.d.; 165924 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Invoices and Purchase Orders, 1999-2000; 165925 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - IP Survey, 2005; 165926 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Lab Instructor Position, 1989; 165927 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Library Reserve Procedures, 1998; 165928 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Memos, Departmental, 1989-1991; 165929 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Memos, Interdepartmental, 1989-1990; 165930 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Memos, Interdepartmental, 1991; 165931 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Memos, Interdepartmental, 1992; 165932 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Memos, Interdepartmental, 1993; 165933 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Memos, Interdepartmental, 1994; 165934 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Memos, Interdepartmental, 1995; 165935 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Memos, Interdepartmental, 1996; 165936 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Microscopes and Disecting Scopes Inventory, 1989; 165937 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Network Installation, 1989; 165939 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - NSF/NIH Graduate Student Survey, 2004-2007; 165940 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Office Relocation, 2002-2004; 165941 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Office of Sponsored Research, 1990-992; 165942 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Philpott, Charles W., 1937-1979; 165943 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Philpott, Charles W., 1980-2000; 165944 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Procedure for Assistant and Associate Professors, 1965-1990; 165945 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Radiation License, 1992; 165946 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Report to the President, Enrollment, 1989-1990; 165947 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Report to the President, Enrollment, 1993; 165948 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Report to the President, Enrollment, 1998; 165949 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Report from the External Advisory Committee for EEB, Oct. 1999; 165950 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Research Doctorate Programs in the U.S., 1995; 165951 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Rice News, Regarding EEB, 1998-1999; 165952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Saftey, 1990-1992; 165953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Seminar Flyers, 1998-1999; 165954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Seminar Worksheets, n.d.; 165955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Space Survey, 1992; 165956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Space Survey, 1997-2001; 165957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Space Survey, 2004-2005; 165958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Tenure and Promotion Guidelines, 1991; 165959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tuition Worksheets, 1985-1989; 165960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Tuition Worksheets, 1990-1997; 165961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Tuition Worksheets, 1998-2000; 165962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Tuition Worksheets, 2001-2003; 165963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Web Applications Security Summary Report, 2000; 165964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Webspace Training, 2006; 165965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Wiess School Strategic Plan, 1997; 165966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Series II. Oversized materials, 167253
  - Glass beeker and still, 167254 (Box 4)